Hello world. Have you ever wondered what
working with an architect in Japan is
like? Well, let's be real, probably not.
That being said, I've actually hired and
worked with an architect for the
buildout of this three-unit mini hotel
called Silver Daisy Stay Nico. Come,
please stay here. We'd be happy to
welcome you. And I've learned a lot
through the process. And I thought by
sharing it with you, you might learn a
little as well. or if not just find the
whole process a bit interesting. It took
nearly 2 years from when we first made
contact with our architect
until we were able to open up our hotel.
As you could imagine, a lot of things
didn't go as planned. There was stress,
there was joy, and a lot of decisions
that needed to be made. So, let's start
at the beginning. Hiring a builder or
architect.
Thanks to Wise for sponsoring this
video.
I think the norm is that most people in
Japan buy a home that's already
pre-built. The design is whatever the
developer thought would sell while
making them a good profit. These are
what you would consider cookie cutter
homes. The next most popular option is
probably going to a builder that can
handle both the design and construction
under one roof. A single company that
does it all. A super easy way to find
one is to go to a model home park. Here
you can see the designs of many
different builders in one place. It's
like a permanent trade show or
exhibition hall. The nice thing about
this is that you can easily imagine what
your home might be like. Kind of like
visiting IKEA, but instead of a single
room, you can see a whole house. But the
one thing about these big builders is
that they do have a certain template to
their designs and a set list of vendors
whose fixtures you're either required to
or encouraged to use. It's kind of like
starting your design based on a limited
set of models which you can modify, but
there are limits. There are smaller
builders as well. We found one online
that did a lot of vacation homes in
Toigi, the prefecture where we built
Silver Daisy. They even had an event at
one of their model homes where they
offered up a free basic design. So, we
got it, but we felt the design was kind
of generic and that a lot of our wishes
on our list, which to be honest was
long, weren't incorporated. It might
have been if we had met again, we would
have found that the basic design was the
starting point and we could have really
shaped the place into what we wanted.
However, when we went the total custom
route, contacting an architect directly,
we found the best fit. We wanted someone
that could look at our specific piece of
land, listen to all our desires, and
design something that tried to fulfill
them. We also wanted someone that can
handhold us along the whole process of
opening up a hotel. So, we wanted help
with not only the building, but buying
the land, testing the soil, getting the
required permits, and all the while
telling us everything was going to be
okay. Yes, we'd have to hire a general
contractor to take our architect's
vision and make it a reality, but for
what we wanted to do, this felt the most
right. The biggest reason we hired our
architect was because he showed so much
passion for the project. And he did so
much for us before we even officially
hired him. For example, without us even
asking, he came to the site multiple
times to measure out things and to
figure out what kind of buildings could
be placed here. He also contacted the
city to make sure that we could get a
hotel license. and also he confirmed
that we could build on the site without
having to redo the retaining wall over
there, which would have been very
expensive. So, in order to move forward
and get an initial design, we had to pay
$50,000 yen, which was about $300 at the
time. This was basically saying, "Let's
try and build something together." Kind
of like a promise ring. We could always
break it off, but the intention was that
we would make it work. So, after we paid
our fee, we waited a couple months and
then we got a call from our architect to
say, "Come to my office and check out
what I came up with." And before I get
to that presentation, I thought it would
be a good time to mention how I moved
money from Canada to Japan to buy the
land and pay for the construction of my
hotel. I used a mix of services with the
main one being Wise. And if you don't
know about Wise, Wise lets you send and
spend money globally. The thing I like
about Wise is that they're upfront about
their fees. In comparison to traditional
bank transfers where banks can charge
fees that aren't always made clear
upfront, including markups on the
exchange rate, I found Wise's fees to be
very competitive. And it's easy to
double check as they're very transparent
about their pricing. using their online
calculator, you'll get a complete
breakdown of all the fees before you
even start. As you can see in this
breakdown, for large transfers over
$25,000,
Wise offers an additional discount. This
is obviously quite beneficial when
you're moving large amounts of money,
like when you're moving from one country
to another or when you need to purchase
property like I did for building my
hotel. But the thing about moving large
amounts of money like this is that it
often triggers KYC,
know your customer regulations. This is
where the banks are required to get
documentation on where you got the money
you're sending from. So, if you've
dipped into your savings, sold property,
sold investments, or received an
inheritance, you'd need to show the
paper trail of that money. What's really
nice about large transfers with Wise is
that they offer a dedicated support
specialist that can guide you through
the whole process. Instead of navigating
everything alone, trying to read through
a variety of websites and online
discussions, the large transfer
specialist can walk you through what you
need to do step by step. They can help
you prepare the documentation ahead of
time and help answer your questions
about international transfers, which can
get complex. Once connected, you can use
the same specialist on future transfers.
In this day and age of automated chat
bots, it's nice that you can connect to
a real human being and even schedule a
phone call to talk to them if you like.
If you have to move large amounts of
money between countries, I think it's a
no-brainer to check out Wise, especially
since it's so easy to see their rates
using their online calculator. So, I
encourage you to sign up for Wise using
the link in the description where you'll
get your first transfer fee free up to
$600 the next time you send money. The
presentation
He wanted our hotel to not only fit in
with nature, but the built-up
surroundings like these cobblestone
streets down below are the street lamps
up above. The stone wells where nearby
spring water flows out from are the
surrounding homes.
So his idea was instead of having one
big building you drop on the place, you
make six small separate buildings.
Side note, in Japan they still use the
term tubo for size measurements. It's
their way of giving the middle finger to
the whole imperial versus metric debate.
The easiest way to visualize it is to
think about two tatami mats right here.
So, two of these equal one tubo.
Interestingly, I'm near Tokyo right now.
So, these mats are actually smaller than
those in Kyoto. However, luckily,
they've standardized the measurement in
meters. So one tubo equals roughly 3.3 m
in metric or 35 square ft in imperial.
So when Arisan says the footprint of the
building will be 18 tubo, that's the
equivalent of 59 square meters or 640
square feet.
He also pointed out that having select
views will block out unwanted visual
noise like the other buildings, wires or
cars. As you walk between the buildings,
your heart will flutter with
anticipation and joy as you experience
different views. And when you get into
the buildings with their various floor
heights, you'll again experience the
views a new
I have to say it was exciting when
Arisam pulled out the blueprints for the
hotel. It was immediately much more
clear what his intentions were. And then
he presented the 3D render of the place.
I am
black.
We were laughing at the library of
assets that came along with the software
as they only had European people and
cars. But then again, at least for the
people, it was not too far off from the
real life visitors we've received so
far. But the best way to get a sense of
what Arisa wanted to build was the
physical model he presented to us.
>> Oh.
That's cool.
>> Wait, that's cool.
>> Obviously, presenting this physical
model was a real boss move. Beyond
physically walking around the real
units, this is the best way I can think
of to figure out what the building will
look like and how everything works out.
But I should say that being able to
manipulate the 3D design in real time
was also a very cool tool. So
ahoki
hi
>> the reason I wanted to look inside the
bathroom was because I wanted to explore
the possibility of a bigger window as
one of my dreams was to be able to look
out onto the mountain while enjoying the
bath. The fact that we could try out
different designs right away made it
much easier and quicker to hash out the
various ideas we all had
cuz Canadians always like windows
windows windows right
windows were one of the areas where we
didn't see eye to eye on. The architect
wanted less, I wanted more. In the end,
we compromised and put in more windows.
And generally, I felt the balance worked
out. Initially, there were no windows in
a couple of the lofts, but I was fairly
adamant about having them in. When
Arisan's wife came to visit, it's one of
the first things she pointed out that
she liked, and I was like, "Ha, in your
face."
We were all laughing about it, but I
would like to admit that over this way
in the bathing room, this window I made
a lot bigger. And you know what? I could
make it a lot smaller. Like a cut a
third off of hair and it' be fine. So, a
lot closer to Aisan's original design.
All in all, I'm glad that I added eight
additional windows and that I pushed
back against Adisan's original design
and that he was so accommodating with my
requests. Something that I was surprised
to see after reviewing this footage,
which is more than a year ago after I
met with that, is that I asked about the
height of the ceilings.
Yeah.
Balance. Yeah. But that's
>> Oh, you'd have to make the other one
taller, too.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Just to balance it.
>> Yeah.
>> So, if you make it taller, the other one
has to be taller, too.
>> I mean, are you are you legally able to
do it? Is there any problem with it?
>> Yeah. 90s. 90s.
>> Huh. Then, honestly, I might not mind
that. Again, this was surprising because
at the end of the day, I wouldn't have
minded if the ceilings in the lofts were
a few feet or a meter higher. Or perhaps
the pitch of the slope were a little
less steep so that the average person
wouldn't need to duck down.
This guest storage was one of those
things that because we were working with
an architect, I think we were able to
add without too much trouble. On the
same presentation day, we also went in
person to the land we were to build on.
There we walked around discussing where
the various buildings would be placed.
Tell us
for
Hi. Hi. Hi. Hi. Hi.
>> While we did spend a lot of time
pretending to be having a tea party in
our imaginary hotel, it was practical to
be at the location to help translate
what was on paper to the real world. The
following week, we went back to Adisan's
office to hash out a few notes we had
about the design. This time, he started
showing us 2D paper printouts of the 3D
design, which yet again gave us another
perspective on how the future hotel
would be like.
Thank you. Thank you.
And so then what happens then? There's a
whole like
>> Oh, then this gets
>> Yeah, I think that's fine. Then you
raise it.
>> Now I'm going to highlight a few more
conversations we had so you can get an
idea of the multitude of things we had
to think about when it comes to
designing and building a place. Like a
frustration of mine was a lack of places
to plug my electronics into.
>> And then other people I talk to too like
about house building, they're always
like whatever they say like you always
get like double. You never regret it.
And I feel the exact same way.
So, yeah, I requested about double the
amount of electrical outlets you'd
usually stick in a place. And you know
what? It's fantastic.
>> Okay, that's interesting.
>> Do you do you think you will use that
area? A very real challenge was having
to make decisions on the spot where
sometimes you really don't know. And as
I'd find out, every decision you make
will have knock-on effects. For example,
if you raise the floor, then you're
going to have less space up in the loft,
unless you also raise the roof. But if
you raise the roof, then it'll be out of
balance with all the other roofs from
the other units. So, what do you do?
What Arisan was saying was that we can
get multiple quotes from different
builders. Since we were working with an
architect, we had to hire a builder, a
Komaen, to help turn Aisan's plan into
reality.
Right? So, another thing was that we
wanted to use local crafts people for
certain items like uh these tatami's
hair. So, what Aayasan was saying was
that we could use our local people
instead of the vendors that would show
up in the estimate because we weren't
working with a national builder. This is
something that we could do.
So yeah, after our initial meeting, we
had a lot of questions and those couple
of pages, those were our questions and
Adisan's responses. I guess it's not so
common to have so many. Uh, in the end
though, I was very happy to have asked
all those questions in advance before
things got started, as I would have
regretted a lot of things if I had
stayed silent.
Hi.
Once we received the estimate from our
builder, it was of course a higher than
what we were expecting. So this was
saying that we could adjust the
materials or our plans in order to lower
the cost.
>> In yet another follow-up meeting, we
started to discuss lighting. In all the
uh renders and plans, there was actually
not any lighting inside. So I was having
a hard time getting a sense of all the
lighting that was going to be used. This
was actually the same thing for the
flooring, for the walls, for the roof,
for the siding. What Arisan first
presented was the structure itself, kind
of like a naked body. How we would go to
dress it up were all decisions that
needed to be made. So, we went on to
visit showrooms like Panasonics and
Lixels. We picked out the portions of
lumber that would be exposed and
visible. We gathered Oya stones for our
future wall. stones that are only found
in a very small area in a nearby town.
And we also chose traditional handmade
paper washi from another nearby town.
When I get around to making the build
part of the series, I'll show it all in
more detail. I think by far my biggest
takeaway from the whole experience was
that even though I had to make hundreds
of decisions, the architect,
he had to make thousands of them. And
because we weren't going off a template,
there were so many unknowns. I don't
know if Aisan will believe this, but as
much as possible, I tried to go with
whatever he was recommending. I don't
have any experience with this. So, I was
trying to trust that whatever he thought
was the best was the best. On the other
hand, when it seems like there are
infinite choices, having some set of
criteria, some guidelines, some vision
for what you're going for seems
essential. And I think that's the role
that my wife, myself, her sister, and
our imaginary guests had to play in this
whole thing. For Arisan to do his job,
he needed to know what we wanted, which
meant we needed to have an opinion on
things. So many things. Would we do it
again? I found the whole process of
working with an architect exciting,
frightening, tiring, and fulfilling. I
thought it was cool, the whole creative
process where you take an idea from your
mind and put it into paper and then from
paper to a building itself. So, for
sure, yes, I'd do it again. Thanks for
watching. See you next time. Peace.
What's working with an architect like
where you're from?
Sign up for Wise using the link in the
description where you'll get your first
transfer fee free up to $600 the next
time you send money.